<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-15T14:30:47-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JAWWS</title><subtitle>Making science more readable to accelerate progress.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Paper Review: Writing Matters</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/14/paper-review-writing-matters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper Review: Writing Matters" /><published>2022-04-14T14:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-14T14:30:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/14/paper-review-writing-matters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/14/paper-review-writing-matters.html">&lt;p&gt;Is it useful to care about the quality of the writing in an academic paper?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer seems obvious, but remember: academic papers aren’t written primarily to communicate ideas. They’re written for the purpose of being accepted at a conference or journal so that you can add them to your academic CV. So, does the quality of your writing increases the odds of being accepted by referees, editors, and conference committees? This is the question studied by Feld et al. in their March 2022 paper “&lt;a href=&quot;https://janfeld.weebly.com/uploads/1/1/8/9/118933153/writing_matters.pdf&quot;&gt;Writing matters&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jan Feld is an economist in New Zealand. The two coauthors, Corinna Lines and Libby Ross, are professional “plain language” consultants. They devised an experiment that consisted of getting unpublished papers from economics PhD students, creating a professionally edited version of each, and asking a bunch of economists and writing experts to rate the quality of a random sample of unedited and edited papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results: Writing experts thoughts that the professionally edited papers were written better, and the economists thought that the professionally edited papers were more likely to be reviewed positively and accepted at conferences and journals. So, writing matters! But by how much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flesch%E2%80%93Kincaid_readability_tests&quot;&gt;Flesch-Kincaid grade level score&lt;/a&gt; estimates what school grade a reader should have to be able to understand a paper. The original, unedited papers had an average score of 15.3 for their introductions (meaning you should be above “grade 15,” so undergraduate level); the edited introductions had an average of 14.7. The chances of accepting a paper for a conference or good journal, according to the economists, were 8.4% higher and 4.1% respectively. Not too surprisingly, these numbers were higher when the unedited version was rated as poorly written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How convincing are these results? An improvement in the Flesch-Kincaid score of less than a year of education doesn’t sound that amazing, and the 1-digit percentage improvements in acceptance rate aren’t mindblowing either. But the authors do conclude that writing matters. They suggest that it would be a good philanthropy cause to offer free professional editing to researchers, especially non-native speakers of English. I think this comes from a logic of “every little bit counts.” Publishing papers in the right places is so important to a scientist’s career, and outside their control for the most part, so you should make sure that each part that you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; control is done well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An obvious limitation is that this study looked at the effect of &lt;em&gt;professional editing&lt;/em&gt;. Professional editing is done by people who are not economists and who will rarely use much creativity in their work — since creativity should stem from the intentions of the original authors. I suspect that this results in papers that avoid the worst, but are also boring and not too interesting. The paper “Writing matters” itself, although clear and fairly easy to read, is rather drab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, this also means that the editing intervention may be scalable, since it is fairly standardized. It also takes into account the scarcity of professional work time: the editors were instructed to spend a reasonable amount of time on any paper, and the total per paper ended up around 6 hours. The authors wrote guidelines emphasizing that most work should be devoted to the title, abstract, and introduction, which are the parts with the highest impact. Any editing done on the rest of the paper should aim at optimizing &lt;em&gt;skimming&lt;/em&gt;, which I like. Few people do more than skimming the methods and results of an academic paper, especially when they need to quickly decide on acceptance or rejection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors published their guidelines in an appendix. They’re pretty good and worth reading. Here is the general outline of the editing process from the appendix:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The goal is to edit the paper so that an expert who has 10 minutes to evaluate the paper will understand it more easily. We’ll focus on improving the title, abstract, and introduction using these guidelines. For the rest of the paper, we’ll focus on making the paper easier to skim read. We’ll prioritise what we edit based on what (in our experience) will best help the reader easily understand the paper while skim reading. We’ll edit for readers who can comfortably read academic documents, but who aren’t familiar with the discipline of economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the writing is very poor, we’ll rewrite some parts instead of editing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are many good reasons we’ll deviate from these guidelines: if it ain’t broke, don’t fix it. If we’re unsure, we’ll ask the writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To save time, we may outsource some tasks to the writers. For example, we might ask them to round all numbers in a table to 2 decimal points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all very reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Is it useful to care about the quality of the writing in an academic paper? The answer seems obvious, but remember: academic papers aren’t written primarily to communicate ideas. They’re written for the purpose of being accepted at a conference or journal so that you can add them to your academic CV. So, does the quality of your writing increases the odds of being accepted by referees, editors, and conference committees? This is the question studied by Feld et al. in their March 2022 paper “Writing matters.” Jan Feld is an economist in New Zealand. The two coauthors, Corinna Lines and Libby Ross, are professional “plain language” consultants. They devised an experiment that consisted of getting unpublished papers from economics PhD students, creating a professionally edited version of each, and asking a bunch of economists and writing experts to rate the quality of a random sample of unedited and edited papers. The results: Writing experts thoughts that the professionally edited papers were written better, and the economists thought that the professionally edited papers were more likely to be reviewed positively and accepted at conferences and journals. So, writing matters! But by how much? The Flesch-Kincaid grade level score estimates what school grade a reader should have to be able to understand a paper. The original, unedited papers had an average score of 15.3 for their introductions (meaning you should be above “grade 15,” so undergraduate level); the edited introductions had an average of 14.7. The chances of accepting a paper for a conference or good journal, according to the economists, were 8.4% higher and 4.1% respectively. Not too surprisingly, these numbers were higher when the unedited version was rated as poorly written. How convincing are these results? An improvement in the Flesch-Kincaid score of less than a year of education doesn’t sound that amazing, and the 1-digit percentage improvements in acceptance rate aren’t mindblowing either. But the authors do conclude that writing matters. They suggest that it would be a good philanthropy cause to offer free professional editing to researchers, especially non-native speakers of English. I think this comes from a logic of “every little bit counts.” Publishing papers in the right places is so important to a scientist’s career, and outside their control for the most part, so you should make sure that each part that you do control is done well. An obvious limitation is that this study looked at the effect of professional editing. Professional editing is done by people who are not economists and who will rarely use much creativity in their work — since creativity should stem from the intentions of the original authors. I suspect that this results in papers that avoid the worst, but are also boring and not too interesting. The paper “Writing matters” itself, although clear and fairly easy to read, is rather drab. On the bright side, this also means that the editing intervention may be scalable, since it is fairly standardized. It also takes into account the scarcity of professional work time: the editors were instructed to spend a reasonable amount of time on any paper, and the total per paper ended up around 6 hours. The authors wrote guidelines emphasizing that most work should be devoted to the title, abstract, and introduction, which are the parts with the highest impact. Any editing done on the rest of the paper should aim at optimizing skimming, which I like. Few people do more than skimming the methods and results of an academic paper, especially when they need to quickly decide on acceptance or rejection. The authors published their guidelines in an appendix. They’re pretty good and worth reading. Here is the general outline of the editing process from the appendix: The goal is to edit the paper so that an expert who has 10 minutes to evaluate the paper will understand it more easily. We’ll focus on improving the title, abstract, and introduction using these guidelines. For the rest of the paper, we’ll focus on making the paper easier to skim read. We’ll prioritise what we edit based on what (in our experience) will best help the reader easily understand the paper while skim reading. We’ll edit for readers who can comfortably read academic documents, but who aren’t familiar with the discipline of economics. If the writing is very poor, we’ll rewrite some parts instead of editing. There are many good reasons we’ll deviate from these guidelines: if it ain’t broke, don’t fix it. If we’re unsure, we’ll ask the writer. To save time, we may outsource some tasks to the writers. For example, we might ask them to round all numbers in a table to 2 decimal points. This is all very reasonable.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/matteucci.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/matteucci.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Browsing Paper Copies of Nature and Science</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/22/browsing-paper-copies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Browsing Paper Copies of Nature and Science" /><published>2022-03-22T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-22T12:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/22/browsing-paper-copies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/22/browsing-paper-copies.html">&lt;p&gt;Most people’s experience of scientific papers, if they have any, consists of downloaded PDFs and articles read directly on the websites of publishers. But of course “papers” are called that because they used to be printed on, well, paper. And some still are! Including everyone’s favorite über-prestigious weekly generalist journals, &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get a better feel for what these two journals are in print, so I went to my local library and picked up a relatively recent copy of each. (I also wanted to check out &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt;, but they didn’t have it; this isn’t a university library.) Here’s a little write-up of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nature-science.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; style=&quot;display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;science&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/toc/science/375/6581&quot;&gt;volume 375, no 6581, 11 February 2022 issue&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; has 107 pages and a cool purple cover that shows the structure of a starfish skeleton from up close. It opens with some ads and then &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; editorials by the same editor-in-chief somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/science-two-editorials.png&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; style=&quot;display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the magazine is organized in three sections: News, Insights, and Research. The News section starts with two pages of short science news (one paragraph each) followed by six news articles (about one page each). The section is capped off by a 4-page “feature” article about robots used in education for children who are stuck at home; in other words, a piece of relatively long-form journalism. All of this is written not by researchers,but by science journalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next section is called “Insights,” whatever that’s supposed to mean. It opens with two pages of random opinions by scientists on whether social media is good or evil (final score: 15 for good, 8 for evil). The next two articles are on the same theme of social media and are apparently authored by experts on science communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/science-social-media.png&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; style=&quot;display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is five Insights “perspective” articles that confuse me a little bit. They’re all essentially summaries and popularizations of articles found later in the Research section. Their authors seem to be specialists in the relevant fields, but they’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the authors of the Research articles. For instance, one is about the cover issue, starfish skeletons: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abn2717&quot;&gt;Starfish grow extraordinary crystals&lt;/a&gt;, by Stephen T. Hyde and Fiona C. Meldrum. It refers to another article titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abj9472&quot;&gt;A damage-tolerant, dual-scale, single-crystalline microlattice in the knobby starfish, &lt;em&gt;Protoreaster nodosus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;by Yang et al. Hyde and Meldrum are professors of chemistry and materials science, but they’re not among the authors of the research article. The same pattern holds for the next four perspective articles. So it seems that &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; is asking scientists to write about other scientists’ work in a more accessible way. This is good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Insights section ends with an obituary and two book reviews, and then we get to the main attraction: the Research section. First, we have a dozen very short summaries of papers either from the &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; family of journals or from the wider literature. Then, four 1-page “research articles summaries” that read as complete but very short papers, each with an intro, a rationale, the results, a conclusion, and one figure. They all state that you can read the full article online. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abi5965&quot;&gt;Here’s an example&lt;/a&gt;. The “Structured Abstract” on that page is what appears in print (and that’s all you’ll get if you don’t have a subscription to &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/science-read-full-online.png&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; style=&quot;display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 60 pages left to this issue — more than half — when we finally get to the “research articles.” Those are long: 7-8 pages in print. There are also only two of them. I assume they’re the most prestigious part of the magazine, since they’re not shortened in any way and their tiny number means it must be difficult to be selected. Indeed, the &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; website’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/content/page/science-information-authors&quot;&gt;page on Information for authors&lt;/a&gt; mentions that they “are expected to present a major advance.” Slightly shorter (4-5 pages) are the remaining eight “reports,” including the starfish one I mentioned earlier. These have to “present important new research results of broad significance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the issue, we get a few more ads and a cute 1-page personal story by some scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nature&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I notice is that &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; is thicker than &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;. This issue — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/nature/volumes/600/issues/7890&quot;&gt;volume 600, no. 7890, 23/30 December 2021&lt;/a&gt; contains 209 pages, so about twice as many as its American counterpart. (&lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; is a British journal.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; opens with a (single) editorial, a “world view” (an opinion piece by some prominent person) and then some news, first “in brief” and then “in focus.” Since this was the last edition of 2021, we get a cool “best images of the year” thing, and then a 14-page-long feature that contains 10 short pieces on scientists who illustrated themselves last year. This feature, not a research article, is also what’s on the cover of the entire issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nature-images.png&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; style=&quot;display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The News and Views section that follows seems to be the equivalent of the Perspective articles in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;: seven short, clear pieces written by experts about research published by other authors elsewhere in the issue. After this comes a 2021 retrospective (I’m starting to think this wasn’t a good example of a typical issue) and then we get the first “Article.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Articles” in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; are 3-6 pages long, similar to the “Reports” in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; There doesn’t seem to be anything longer. But there are many more: twenty-six in this issue. Even if they’re short, they’re full articles, as opposed to abridged versions of something longer on the website. So in a way, &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; seems more egalitarian than &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;: nothing is given more status than the rest, and all articles are expected to have a similar format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue ends with several articles on science as a workplace and professional activity: there are pieces on the state of scientific work, issues with alcohol at science events, and some tips for event organizers as well as people who want to tell more compelling stories in their presentations. (“State your main finding in your title, and don’t forget to use the word ‘but’.”) There’s a calendar of networking events, a bunch of ads throughout, and, at the very end, a cute 1-page personal story by some scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; were explicitly created with a dual aim: communicate results between scientists, and from scientists from the public. Even though they are now known more for their research articles — and the prestige that they offer to the few researchers who manage to be selected — they still carry their mission of popularizing science, partly through those hybrid “perspective” and “news and views” papers. This seems like an overall good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that is more difficult to do online (despite the invention of the web browser!) is simply browsing through and randomly stumbling on interesting articles. This was actually a concern for the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; staff back in the 1990s: according to the book &lt;em&gt;Making Nature&lt;/em&gt;, they thought that the advent of the electronic journal would lead to less browsing. I think they were right to a large extent. Even though I wasn’t intending on reading any of the articles, my leafing through print copies made me read a few short things that seemed interesting and that I would likely never have encountered otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve known for years that &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; exist in print. Yet I don’t think I ever saw or opened a copy, even though I have a couple of science degrees. I’m guessing that my experience is not unusual. It may be a good idea for researchers who deal with disembodied papers all the time — both as readers and as authors — to remind themselves what papers actually are, or were.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Most people’s experience of scientific papers, if they have any, consists of downloaded PDFs and articles read directly on the websites of publishers. But of course “papers” are called that because they used to be printed on, well, paper. And some still are! Including everyone’s favorite über-prestigious weekly generalist journals, Nature and Science. I wanted to get a better feel for what these two journals are in print, so I went to my local library and picked up a relatively recent copy of each. (I also wanted to check out Cell, but they didn’t have it; this isn’t a university library.) Here’s a little write-up of the experience. Science The volume 375, no 6581, 11 February 2022 issue of Science has 107 pages and a cool purple cover that shows the structure of a starfish skeleton from up close. It opens with some ads and then two editorials by the same editor-in-chief somehow. The rest of the magazine is organized in three sections: News, Insights, and Research. The News section starts with two pages of short science news (one paragraph each) followed by six news articles (about one page each). The section is capped off by a 4-page “feature” article about robots used in education for children who are stuck at home; in other words, a piece of relatively long-form journalism. All of this is written not by researchers,but by science journalists. The next section is called “Insights,” whatever that’s supposed to mean. It opens with two pages of random opinions by scientists on whether social media is good or evil (final score: 15 for good, 8 for evil). The next two articles are on the same theme of social media and are apparently authored by experts on science communication. What follows is five Insights “perspective” articles that confuse me a little bit. They’re all essentially summaries and popularizations of articles found later in the Research section. Their authors seem to be specialists in the relevant fields, but they’re not the authors of the Research articles. For instance, one is about the cover issue, starfish skeletons: Starfish grow extraordinary crystals, by Stephen T. Hyde and Fiona C. Meldrum. It refers to another article titled A damage-tolerant, dual-scale, single-crystalline microlattice in the knobby starfish, Protoreaster nodosusby Yang et al. Hyde and Meldrum are professors of chemistry and materials science, but they’re not among the authors of the research article. The same pattern holds for the next four perspective articles. So it seems that Science is asking scientists to write about other scientists’ work in a more accessible way. This is good! The Insights section ends with an obituary and two book reviews, and then we get to the main attraction: the Research section. First, we have a dozen very short summaries of papers either from the Science family of journals or from the wider literature. Then, four 1-page “research articles summaries” that read as complete but very short papers, each with an intro, a rationale, the results, a conclusion, and one figure. They all state that you can read the full article online. Here’s an example. The “Structured Abstract” on that page is what appears in print (and that’s all you’ll get if you don’t have a subscription to Science). There are 60 pages left to this issue — more than half — when we finally get to the “research articles.” Those are long: 7-8 pages in print. There are also only two of them. I assume they’re the most prestigious part of the magazine, since they’re not shortened in any way and their tiny number means it must be difficult to be selected. Indeed, the Science website’s page on Information for authors mentions that they “are expected to present a major advance.” Slightly shorter (4-5 pages) are the remaining eight “reports,” including the starfish one I mentioned earlier. These have to “present important new research results of broad significance.” At the end of the issue, we get a few more ads and a cute 1-page personal story by some scientist. Nature The first thing I notice is that Nature is thicker than Science. This issue — volume 600, no. 7890, 23/30 December 2021 contains 209 pages, so about twice as many as its American counterpart. (Nature is a British journal.) Nature opens with a (single) editorial, a “world view” (an opinion piece by some prominent person) and then some news, first “in brief” and then “in focus.” Since this was the last edition of 2021, we get a cool “best images of the year” thing, and then a 14-page-long feature that contains 10 short pieces on scientists who illustrated themselves last year. This feature, not a research article, is also what’s on the cover of the entire issue. The News and Views section that follows seems to be the equivalent of the Perspective articles in Science: seven short, clear pieces written by experts about research published by other authors elsewhere in the issue. After this comes a 2021 retrospective (I’m starting to think this wasn’t a good example of a typical issue) and then we get the first “Article.” “Articles” in Nature are 3-6 pages long, similar to the “Reports” in Science There doesn’t seem to be anything longer. But there are many more: twenty-six in this issue. Even if they’re short, they’re full articles, as opposed to abridged versions of something longer on the website. So in a way, Nature seems more egalitarian than Science: nothing is given more status than the rest, and all articles are expected to have a similar format. The issue ends with several articles on science as a workplace and professional activity: there are pieces on the state of scientific work, issues with alcohol at science events, and some tips for event organizers as well as people who want to tell more compelling stories in their presentations. (“State your main finding in your title, and don’t forget to use the word ‘but’.”) There’s a calendar of networking events, a bunch of ads throughout, and, at the very end, a cute 1-page personal story by some scientist. Conclusion Nature and Science were explicitly created with a dual aim: communicate results between scientists, and from scientists from the public. Even though they are now known more for their research articles — and the prestige that they offer to the few researchers who manage to be selected — they still carry their mission of popularizing science, partly through those hybrid “perspective” and “news and views” papers. This seems like an overall good thing. One thing that is more difficult to do online (despite the invention of the web browser!) is simply browsing through and randomly stumbling on interesting articles. This was actually a concern for the Nature staff back in the 1990s: according to the book Making Nature, they thought that the advent of the electronic journal would lead to less browsing. I think they were right to a large extent. Even though I wasn’t intending on reading any of the articles, my leafing through print copies made me read a few short things that seemed interesting and that I would likely never have encountered otherwise. I’ve known for years that Nature and Science exist in print. Yet I don’t think I ever saw or opened a copy, even though I have a couple of science degrees. I’m guessing that my experience is not unusual. It may be a good idea for researchers who deal with disembodied papers all the time — both as readers and as authors — to remind themselves what papers actually are, or were.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/nature-science.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/nature-science.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: The Sense of Style</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/09/book-review-sense-of-style.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: The Sense of Style" /><published>2022-03-09T13:46:31-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-09T13:46:31-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/09/book-review-sense-of-style</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/09/book-review-sense-of-style.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This book review was first published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.substack.com/p/book-review-the-sense-of-style&quot;&gt;Atlas of Wonders and Monsters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you write essays or academic papers in the English language, then you must absolutely read Steven Pinker’s 2014 writing guide, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stevenpinker.com/publications/sense-style-thinking-persons-guide-writing-21st-century&quot;&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Realistically, you won’t (who has time to read books, anyway?), so at least read this review of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinker’s book can be read as an updated — and partial takedown — of older guides like Strunk and White’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Elements_of_Style&quot;&gt;The Elements of Style&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. It does contain plenty of rules and advice, especially in the sixth and last chapter, which provides an overview of many common problems of vocabulary, grammar, and punctuation, with abundant detail. But this part is the least interesting one, especially if you’re the kind of person who already pays attention to the rules of language. Most of the value of the book is in the first few chapters, where Pinker discusses two concepts I hadn’t seen presented in this way before: &lt;strong&gt;classic style&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;the curse of knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55394bf8-d7b0-487c-a920-3c9938dd798e_4032x3024.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55394bf8-d7b0-487c-a920-3c9938dd798e_4032x3024.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;classic-style&quot;&gt;Classic Style&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s trivial to say that writing can be done in many different styles. It’s trickier to &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; those styles, let alone pick one as the generally superior option. Pinker identifies a good candidate, one that has been around since French writers like René Descartes invented it in the 17th century: classic style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing styles can be described with metaphors of human experience. For instance, “practical style” fits the metaphor of a someone teaching something to a student. One of the two main metaphors for classic style is “&lt;strong&gt;a window onto the world&lt;/strong&gt;.” The goal is to show the reader something true that the writer has noticed but the reader may not have yet. In this metaphor, the writer knows the truth and simply presents it, in clear language, without formally arguing for it. The other metaphor for classic style is &lt;strong&gt;a conversation between writer and reader&lt;/strong&gt;. The two are equals, seeking truth together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classic style has several cool properties. One is that it trusts the reader to be a competent adult. This makes the reading experience more enjoyable than being treated as an immature child or an enemy. In fact, when done well, classic style “makes the reader feel like a genius.” You feel understood, smart, appreciated, just like after having a meaningful conversation with somebody you know and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another property of classic style is that it emphasizes natural human behaviors: seeing (the window metaphor) and talking (the conversation one). By contrast, writing is unnatural: it involves memorizing a bunch of bizarre symbols and learning how to make meaningful strings out of them. Therefore, to ease the weigh on the reader’s shoulder, it’s better to focus on seeing and talking, which are innate. Hence the common advice to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Show,_don%27t_tell&quot;&gt;show, don’t tell&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/talk.html&quot;&gt;write like you talk&lt;/a&gt;, two hallmarks of classic style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third property is requiring the writer to pretend they already know the truth. In classic style, you don’t use the writing process to figure out what you’re trying to say. Of course, it’s perfectly fine to actually figure out what you’re trying to say through writing — you &lt;em&gt;pretend&lt;/em&gt; to already know the truth, even though in practice you probably learned it along the way — but then you should strip your final draft of any traces of your thought process. Readers are generally interested in the truth you’re presenting, not your personal story of finding that truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, classic style is not the only style around. It is appropriate for essays, blog posts, articles, anything aimed at generic readership; but not necessarily for highly technical writing, instruction manuals, didactic material, or political speeches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the other styles Pinker mentions, and how do they contrast with classic style?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contemplative or romantic style&lt;/strong&gt;: Here the goal is to express the writer’s emotional reaction to something. Good for diaries, poetry, songs, some fiction, personal essays, etc. Less concerned with the objective truth than classic style is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prophetic, oracular, or oratorical style&lt;/strong&gt;: The writer attempts to unite their audience with language used as music, and the gift of seeing things that no one else can. Good for political speeches or religious sermons. Assumes a one-to-many relationship as opposed to the one-to-one of classic style.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical style&lt;/strong&gt;: The writer and reader have well-defined roles, usually something along the lines of teacher and student. The writer seeks to transmit information that the reader needs. Good for manuals, schoolwork, research reports, memos, recipes, etc. This contrasts with the equality between reader and writer in classic style.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plain style&lt;/strong&gt;: This one is more subtle, and not so different from classic style. Pinker says that plain style puts everything in clear view, with simple language, whereas classic style makes the reader work a bit to get to the truth. I’m not sure I fully grasp the distinction, but I do like this example. I suggest you take&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Plain: “The early bird gets the worm.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Classic: “The early bird gets the worm, but the second mouse gets the cheese.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-conscious, relativistic, ironic, and postmodern styles&lt;/strong&gt;: This family of styles contrasts with classic style in its emphasis on abstract philosophical questions, like “what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; truth?” Such questions tend to hinder the quest to actually present truth. Pinker provides us with some delightful takedowns of stuffy postmodern academic prose that not only makes readers feel stupid, but also manages to say almost nothing about the world. He does mention, though, that everyone is always a bit postmodern; our relationship with truth is complex and full of biases, which we need to be aware of. But in classic style, you have to “artfully conceal [anxieties about truth] for clarity’s sake.” Philosophical questions otherwise just get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These styles are not clearly delineated, and any piece of writing can involve a mix of them. But practicing classic style — and the various pieces of advice Pinker gives us to do so, like avoiding excessive metadiscourse,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; zombie nouns, clichés, passive voice, and abstract thought — can help us improve all writing, including academic papers. Classic style is an ideal: not something we can always pull off, but something we should generally strive towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-curse-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;The Curse of Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steven Pinker is first and foremost a cognitive scientist. which is relevant for this section on what is going on in the mind of writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse of knowledge is “a difficulty in imagining what it is like for someone else not to know something that you know.” This concept, Pinker points out, keeps being rediscovered, and so it goes by many names. &lt;em&gt;Curse of knowledge&lt;/em&gt; is a term originally from economics. In various subfields of psychology, the same idea has been called &lt;em&gt;egocentrism&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;hindsight bias&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;false consensus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;illusion transparency&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;mindblindness&lt;/em&gt;. I have myself written about similar ideas such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/nothing-is-inherently-obvious/&quot;&gt;obviousness&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.substack.com/p/the-secret-sauce-of-everything-good&quot;&gt;awareness and empathy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinker says that the curse of knowledge is “a pervasive drag on the strivings of humanity, on a par with corruption, disease, and entropy.” Nothing less. He also says that it is “the single best explanation I know of why good people write bad prose.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with both these assessments. The crux, then, is in how to lift the curse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;the reader&lt;/em&gt;. This is not sufficient, because we are bad at empathy and can’t model other people accurately. So our guesses as to what readers know are often wrong: we tend, for example, to think that what is obvious to us is obvious to everyone. But I suspect that so few people actually use this simple trick that it’s worth repeating often. &lt;strong&gt;Put yourself in your reader’s shoes&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the first and most important lesson for a writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinker’s specific advice to deal with the curse mirrors what I’ve been writing about in my exploration of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/04/scientific-style-guide.html&quot;&gt;ideal scientific style&lt;/a&gt;. For instance, avoid the excessive use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/05/abbreviations.html&quot;&gt;abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;, since “the few seconds they add to [the writers’] lives come at the cost of many minutes stolen from the lives of their readers.” Avoid jargon: &lt;em&gt;murine models&lt;/em&gt; is almost always worse than &lt;em&gt;rats and mice&lt;/em&gt;. Add short explanations to any technical terms you must use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A writer who explains technical terms can multiply her readership a thousandfold at the cost of a handful of characters, the literary equivalent of picking up hundred-dollar bills on the sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more: use plenty of examples, avoid Latin phrases that have an English equivalent, pick the clearest possible technical terms, use concrete imagery that stimulates the senses (“a quiet room” instead of “conditions of good acoustic isolation”), and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two concepts from cognitive science support Pinker’s arguments: chunking and functional fixity. &lt;strong&gt;Chunking&lt;/strong&gt; — which has a pleasantly simple and evocative name! — is the phenomenon of repackaging information into units that occupy a single slot in our limited working memory. Remembering a string of digits like 4-7-1-0-5-4 (as, say, a passcode) takes six slots and is difficult, but chunk it into 47-10-54 and now it’s only three slots. Assuming you’re used to dealing with two-digit numbers, it’s way more manageable. Maybe you are a history nerd and even recognize that this is the probable date of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SN_1054&quot;&gt;Crab Nebula supernova&lt;/a&gt;: July 4th, 1054.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nice, now this string of six numbers takes a single slot of your working memory!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5aba397c-49eb-44a4-ba69-2100d1f7fcb2_1920x1920.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5aba397c-49eb-44a4-ba69-2100d1f7fcb2_1920x1920.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Crab Nebula.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Crab Nebula.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And now thanks to this visual support you are even more likely to remember this string of six digits forever! (At least,&lt;/em&gt; I &lt;em&gt;am.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chunking explains one of the ways the curse of knowledge afflicts us: it’s because we don’t all have the same chunks. If I want you to learn my passcode and I tell you “the date of the Crab Nebula supernova,” but you have no idea what a supernova even is, then I have failed to consider what you don’t know. The chunk I use is not one that you have in your mind. And if you don’t care about history or supernovae, it might be difficult for you to properly package it into something useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concept that makes the curse of knowledge a curse is &lt;strong&gt;functional fixity&lt;/strong&gt;. This means thinking of things in terms of what they do as opposed to what they are. When you write about a topic you know well, you stop seeing the tangible stuff — colors, shapes, sounds, textures. Such concerns become boring compared to what the thing &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; — which is what you care about when you’re experienced with a topic. Therefore you’ll say “conditions of good acoustic isolation” as opposed to “a quiet room.” But for readers, concrete and sensory wording is better. You have to be mindful of the curse of knowledge for this not to become a hindrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinker ends this chapter by urging writers to think about how other people think and feel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It may not make you a better person in all spheres of life, but it will be a source of continuous kindness yo your readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed. Be kind. And if you’re writing a scientific paper on a complex topic, then be &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;/em&gt; kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-thoughts&quot;&gt;Other Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more in &lt;em&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/em&gt;. I haven’t mentioned the middle two chapters, on syntax (the structure of sentences) and coherence (the structure of paragraphs and entire essays). These were less immediately useful and new to me, but they still contain plenty of good advice. I particularly liked his enumeration of the fourteen types of connections that can exist between ideas (with examples of typical connective words):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarity (“and”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contrast (“but”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elaboration (“in other words”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exemplification (“for example”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generalization (“more generally”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exception after a general statement (“on the other hand”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exception before a general statement (“nonetheless”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sequence: before-and-after (“and then”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sequence: after-and-before (“when”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result (“so”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Explanation (“since”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Violated expectation (“yet”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Failed prevention (“despite”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Attribution (“according to”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently that’s it. Taking into account some inevitable grey areas, these are all the ways that ideas (and therefore sentences and paragraphs) can relate to each other. No need to memorize them, but it’s pretty neat to see them laid out like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the book is worth reading in its entirety. It’s a rather pleasant experience, in part because of how Pinker often quotes comic strips to illustrate a point—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8effc4b0-d9ca-4757-83e5-63e4b3f6fcdc_730x254.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8effc4b0-d9ca-4757-83e5-63e4b3f6fcdc_730x254.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cautionary Ghost&quot; title=&quot;Cautionary Ghost&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/1108/&quot;&gt;xkcd #1108&lt;/a&gt;; but also &lt;a href=&quot;https://qwantz.com/index.php?comic=2079&quot;&gt;Dinosaur Comics&lt;/a&gt;, Calvin and Hobbes, and Dilbert, among others&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—but also because the book is well written (it would have been pretty ironic otherwise) and, importantly, very nuanced. It’s hard to disagree with much in &lt;em&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/em&gt;: Pinker anticipates most objections, and he rarely makes sweeping pronouncements on what is right or wrong. When he does, his pronouncements are backed with persuasive arguments and evidence from psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you think of Pinker as a public intellectual, he is clearly somebody who cares about good writing. As he puts it, style matters for three reasons: it ensures ideas get communicated effectively, it earns the trust of readers, and it adds beauty to the world. These are three worthy goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one problem I have with &lt;em&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/em&gt; is… well, it’s not a problem in the book, but a problem in what I want to do, namely &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/&quot;&gt;improving the readability of science papers&lt;/a&gt;. Since no part of the book is useless, it can’t really be distilled into something that is quickly digestible. That’s not a big surprise: writing is an art that takes years to master, so of course you can’t learn it all in one tweet or blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that it’s not reasonable to expect scientists and grad students to get trained as writers. This book, like most books, requires some investment of time as well as interest in improving the craft of writing. Without time or interest, it will be as useless as any other style guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this book review helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metadiscourse&lt;/em&gt; means discourse about the discourse, such as the words “section” and “discusses” in the sentence “This section discusses two important concepts.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Maybe 4/7/1054 is not the format you’re used to, but you’re able to deal with that, aren’t you? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This book review was first published on Atlas of Wonders and Monsters. If you write essays or academic papers in the English language, then you must absolutely read Steven Pinker’s 2014 writing guide, The Sense of Style. Realistically, you won’t (who has time to read books, anyway?), so at least read this review of it. Pinker’s book can be read as an updated — and partial takedown — of older guides like Strunk and White’s The Elements of Style. It does contain plenty of rules and advice, especially in the sixth and last chapter, which provides an overview of many common problems of vocabulary, grammar, and punctuation, with abundant detail. But this part is the least interesting one, especially if you’re the kind of person who already pays attention to the rules of language. Most of the value of the book is in the first few chapters, where Pinker discusses two concepts I hadn’t seen presented in this way before: classic style and the curse of knowledge. Classic Style It’s trivial to say that writing can be done in many different styles. It’s trickier to name those styles, let alone pick one as the generally superior option. Pinker identifies a good candidate, one that has been around since French writers like René Descartes invented it in the 17th century: classic style. Writing styles can be described with metaphors of human experience. For instance, “practical style” fits the metaphor of a someone teaching something to a student. One of the two main metaphors for classic style is “a window onto the world.” The goal is to show the reader something true that the writer has noticed but the reader may not have yet. In this metaphor, the writer knows the truth and simply presents it, in clear language, without formally arguing for it. The other metaphor for classic style is a conversation between writer and reader. The two are equals, seeking truth together. Classic style has several cool properties. One is that it trusts the reader to be a competent adult. This makes the reading experience more enjoyable than being treated as an immature child or an enemy. In fact, when done well, classic style “makes the reader feel like a genius.” You feel understood, smart, appreciated, just like after having a meaningful conversation with somebody you know and trust. Another property of classic style is that it emphasizes natural human behaviors: seeing (the window metaphor) and talking (the conversation one). By contrast, writing is unnatural: it involves memorizing a bunch of bizarre symbols and learning how to make meaningful strings out of them. Therefore, to ease the weigh on the reader’s shoulder, it’s better to focus on seeing and talking, which are innate. Hence the common advice to show, don’t tell and write like you talk, two hallmarks of classic style. A third property is requiring the writer to pretend they already know the truth. In classic style, you don’t use the writing process to figure out what you’re trying to say. Of course, it’s perfectly fine to actually figure out what you’re trying to say through writing — you pretend to already know the truth, even though in practice you probably learned it along the way — but then you should strip your final draft of any traces of your thought process. Readers are generally interested in the truth you’re presenting, not your personal story of finding that truth. Of course, classic style is not the only style around. It is appropriate for essays, blog posts, articles, anything aimed at generic readership; but not necessarily for highly technical writing, instruction manuals, didactic material, or political speeches. What are the other styles Pinker mentions, and how do they contrast with classic style? Contemplative or romantic style: Here the goal is to express the writer’s emotional reaction to something. Good for diaries, poetry, songs, some fiction, personal essays, etc. Less concerned with the objective truth than classic style is. Prophetic, oracular, or oratorical style: The writer attempts to unite their audience with language used as music, and the gift of seeing things that no one else can. Good for political speeches or religious sermons. Assumes a one-to-many relationship as opposed to the one-to-one of classic style. Practical style: The writer and reader have well-defined roles, usually something along the lines of teacher and student. The writer seeks to transmit information that the reader needs. Good for manuals, schoolwork, research reports, memos, recipes, etc. This contrasts with the equality between reader and writer in classic style. Plain style: This one is more subtle, and not so different from classic style. Pinker says that plain style puts everything in clear view, with simple language, whereas classic style makes the reader work a bit to get to the truth. I’m not sure I fully grasp the distinction, but I do like this example. I suggest you take Plain: “The early bird gets the worm.” Classic: “The early bird gets the worm, but the second mouse gets the cheese.” Self-conscious, relativistic, ironic, and postmodern styles: This family of styles contrasts with classic style in its emphasis on abstract philosophical questions, like “what is truth?” Such questions tend to hinder the quest to actually present truth. Pinker provides us with some delightful takedowns of stuffy postmodern academic prose that not only makes readers feel stupid, but also manages to say almost nothing about the world. He does mention, though, that everyone is always a bit postmodern; our relationship with truth is complex and full of biases, which we need to be aware of. But in classic style, you have to “artfully conceal [anxieties about truth] for clarity’s sake.” Philosophical questions otherwise just get in the way. These styles are not clearly delineated, and any piece of writing can involve a mix of them. But practicing classic style — and the various pieces of advice Pinker gives us to do so, like avoiding excessive metadiscourse,1 zombie nouns, clichés, passive voice, and abstract thought — can help us improve all writing, including academic papers. Classic style is an ideal: not something we can always pull off, but something we should generally strive towards. The Curse of Knowledge Steven Pinker is first and foremost a cognitive scientist. which is relevant for this section on what is going on in the mind of writers. The curse of knowledge is “a difficulty in imagining what it is like for someone else not to know something that you know.” This concept, Pinker points out, keeps being rediscovered, and so it goes by many names. Curse of knowledge is a term originally from economics. In various subfields of psychology, the same idea has been called egocentrism, hindsight bias, false consensus, illusion transparency, and mindblindness. I have myself written about similar ideas such as obviousness and awareness and empathy. Pinker says that the curse of knowledge is “a pervasive drag on the strivings of humanity, on a par with corruption, disease, and entropy.” Nothing less. He also says that it is “the single best explanation I know of why good people write bad prose.” I agree with both these assessments. The crux, then, is in how to lift the curse. The first step is to think about the reader. This is not sufficient, because we are bad at empathy and can’t model other people accurately. So our guesses as to what readers know are often wrong: we tend, for example, to think that what is obvious to us is obvious to everyone. But I suspect that so few people actually use this simple trick that it’s worth repeating often. Put yourself in your reader’s shoes. This is the first and most important lesson for a writer. Pinker’s specific advice to deal with the curse mirrors what I’ve been writing about in my exploration of ideal scientific style. For instance, avoid the excessive use of abbreviations, since “the few seconds they add to [the writers’] lives come at the cost of many minutes stolen from the lives of their readers.” Avoid jargon: murine models is almost always worse than rats and mice. Add short explanations to any technical terms you must use: A writer who explains technical terms can multiply her readership a thousandfold at the cost of a handful of characters, the literary equivalent of picking up hundred-dollar bills on the sidewalk. There’s more: use plenty of examples, avoid Latin phrases that have an English equivalent, pick the clearest possible technical terms, use concrete imagery that stimulates the senses (“a quiet room” instead of “conditions of good acoustic isolation”), and so on. Two concepts from cognitive science support Pinker’s arguments: chunking and functional fixity. Chunking — which has a pleasantly simple and evocative name! — is the phenomenon of repackaging information into units that occupy a single slot in our limited working memory. Remembering a string of digits like 4-7-1-0-5-4 (as, say, a passcode) takes six slots and is difficult, but chunk it into 47-10-54 and now it’s only three slots. Assuming you’re used to dealing with two-digit numbers, it’s way more manageable. Maybe you are a history nerd and even recognize that this is the probable date of the Crab Nebula supernova: July 4th, 1054.2 Nice, now this string of six numbers takes a single slot of your working memory! And now thanks to this visual support you are even more likely to remember this string of six digits forever! (At least, I am.) Chunking explains one of the ways the curse of knowledge afflicts us: it’s because we don’t all have the same chunks. If I want you to learn my passcode and I tell you “the date of the Crab Nebula supernova,” but you have no idea what a supernova even is, then I have failed to consider what you don’t know. The chunk I use is not one that you have in your mind. And if you don’t care about history or supernovae, it might be difficult for you to properly package it into something useful. The other concept that makes the curse of knowledge a curse is functional fixity. This means thinking of things in terms of what they do as opposed to what they are. When you write about a topic you know well, you stop seeing the tangible stuff — colors, shapes, sounds, textures. Such concerns become boring compared to what the thing does — which is what you care about when you’re experienced with a topic. Therefore you’ll say “conditions of good acoustic isolation” as opposed to “a quiet room.” But for readers, concrete and sensory wording is better. You have to be mindful of the curse of knowledge for this not to become a hindrance. Pinker ends this chapter by urging writers to think about how other people think and feel: It may not make you a better person in all spheres of life, but it will be a source of continuous kindness yo your readers. Indeed. Be kind. And if you’re writing a scientific paper on a complex topic, then be extra kind. Other Thoughts There is much more in The Sense of Style. I haven’t mentioned the middle two chapters, on syntax (the structure of sentences) and coherence (the structure of paragraphs and entire essays). These were less immediately useful and new to me, but they still contain plenty of good advice. I particularly liked his enumeration of the fourteen types of connections that can exist between ideas (with examples of typical connective words): Similarity (“and”) Contrast (“but”) Elaboration (“in other words”) Exemplification (“for example”) Generalization (“more generally”) Exception after a general statement (“on the other hand”) Exception before a general statement (“nonetheless”) Sequence: before-and-after (“and then”) Sequence: after-and-before (“when”) Result (“so”) Explanation (“since”) Violated expectation (“yet”) Failed prevention (“despite”) Attribution (“according to”) Apparently that’s it. Taking into account some inevitable grey areas, these are all the ways that ideas (and therefore sentences and paragraphs) can relate to each other. No need to memorize them, but it’s pretty neat to see them laid out like this. In any case, the book is worth reading in its entirety. It’s a rather pleasant experience, in part because of how Pinker often quotes comic strips to illustrate a point— For instance, xkcd #1108; but also Dinosaur Comics, Calvin and Hobbes, and Dilbert, among others —but also because the book is well written (it would have been pretty ironic otherwise) and, importantly, very nuanced. It’s hard to disagree with much in The Sense of Style: Pinker anticipates most objections, and he rarely makes sweeping pronouncements on what is right or wrong. When he does, his pronouncements are backed with persuasive arguments and evidence from psychology. Whatever you think of Pinker as a public intellectual, he is clearly somebody who cares about good writing. As he puts it, style matters for three reasons: it ensures ideas get communicated effectively, it earns the trust of readers, and it adds beauty to the world. These are three worthy goals. The one problem I have with The Sense of Style is… well, it’s not a problem in the book, but a problem in what I want to do, namely improving the readability of science papers. Since no part of the book is useless, it can’t really be distilled into something that is quickly digestible. That’s not a big surprise: writing is an art that takes years to master, so of course you can’t learn it all in one tweet or blog post. The problem is that it’s not reasonable to expect scientists and grad students to get trained as writers. This book, like most books, requires some investment of time as well as interest in improving the craft of writing. Without time or interest, it will be as useless as any other style guide. Hopefully this book review helps. Metadiscourse means discourse about the discourse, such as the words “section” and “discusses” in the sentence “This section discusses two important concepts.” &amp;#8617; Maybe 4/7/1054 is not the format you’re used to, but you’re able to deal with that, aren’t you? &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55394bf8-d7b0-487c-a920-3c9938dd798e_4032x3024.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55394bf8-d7b0-487c-a920-3c9938dd798e_4032x3024.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Time-Honored Tradition of Complaining About Bad Scientific Style</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/09/complaining-about-scientific-writing-is-nothing-new.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Time-Honored Tradition of Complaining About Bad Scientific Style" /><published>2022-03-09T13:46:31-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-09T13:46:31-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/09/complaining-about-scientific-writing-is-nothing-new</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/03/09/complaining-about-scientific-writing-is-nothing-new.html">&lt;p&gt;SlimeMoldTimeMold — https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Scientific_Literature/0Ns56qzBMIUC?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;pg=PA34&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making Nature p. 184&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">SlimeMoldTimeMold — https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Scientific_Literature/0Ns56qzBMIUC?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;pg=PA34&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover Making Nature p. 184</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Style Guide: Figures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/01/16/figures.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Style Guide: Figures" /><published>2022-01-16T16:05:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-16T16:05:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/01/16/figures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/01/16/figures.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#recommendations&quot;&gt;Click here for a summary of the main recommendations&lt;/a&gt; • This essay is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/04/style-guide.html&quot;&gt;science style guide series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figures are the lifeblood of scientific papers. Many people won’t read your paper, but will look at the figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is that? There are many reasons, ranging from being attracted to shiny colors to reducing cognitive load by activating a different part of memory. But I suspect that one of the most important reasons is that figures allow more freedom to writers than text. There are no word limits, fewer formatting constraints, no bad writing style norms. All that matters is that your figure is clear and true. Accordingly, scientists spend a lot of time on them, and they are often the best part of any scientific paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this freedom, I would say that figures are perhaps the part of scientific publishing that works best as thing currently stand. That doesn’t mean we can’t improve on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;captions&quot;&gt;Captions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the norms I observe around figures is that they should be “separate” from the main text. The caption should be sufficient to understand a figure even if someone hasn’t read the text. This is a good idea overall, but it sometimes leads to paragraph-length captions that are as difficult to read as the main text. Not great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journals also usually limit the number of figures you can have in a paper. This can lead to very dense figures, with multiple subparts (Fig. 1A, 1B, 1C, etc.), trying to cram as much information as possible. This is the visual equivalent to a long and dense paragraph. Also not great — plus it makes the captions even longer and confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example figure and caption from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/platypus-paper-rewritten/&quot;&gt;platypus paper I rewrote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/platypus fig 4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fig. 4. (A) Alignment of predicted protein sequence of transcripts containing a recombined VHδ gene isolated from platypus spleen RNA. The individual clones are identified by the last three digits of their GenBank accession numbers (JQ664690–JQ664710). Shown is the region from FR3 of the VHδ through the beginning of the Cδ domain. The sequence in bold at the top of the alignment is the germ-line VHδ and Cδ gene sequence. The double cysteines at the end of FR3 and unpaired cysteines in CDR3 are shaded, as is the canonical FGXG in FR4. (B) Nucleotide sequence of the CDR3 region of the eleven unique V(D)J recombinants using VHδ described in the text. The germ-line sequence of the 3′-end of VHδ, the two Dδ, are shown at the top. The germ-line Jδ sequences are shown on the right-hand side of the alignment interspersed amongst the cDNA sequences using each. Nucleotides in the junctions between the V, D, and J segments, shown italicized, are most likely N-nucleotides added by TdT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure all of it is essential information, so I won’t say that it should be shortened, exactly—although if you can, yes, shorten it! But it’s a &lt;em&gt;figure&lt;/em&gt;. It’s supposed to be visual. As much of the caption as possible should be included directly in the figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the fact that Fig. 4 is in fact Fig. 4A and 4B. The “(B)” is buried in the middle of the caption, with no bolding or anything to make it stand out. Readers have to parse the caption themselves to understand the two parts separately. Plus, the text uses parentheses for normal parenthesis purposes, and even has a “(D)” that doesn’t refer to a hypothetical part D. This is asking a lot of effort from readers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do like the fact that the caption refers to the main text (it says “described in the text” in part B), although it would have been nice if it said where to look exactly in the text. As things stand, the reader has to spend energy to find the spot being referred to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if your caption contains the word “&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt;” or “&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;” or any color, and &lt;em&gt;does not use&lt;/em&gt; the mentioned color, then you’re doing something wrong. Using color directly in a caption, to reference a color-coded part of the figure, helps your reader so much it would be mad not to do so. (There can be technical limitations, of course, but it’s not usually very difficult to add color to text. I wasn’t sure I could do it on this website, and it took three seconds of googling the relevant HTML snippet.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;referencing-a-figure&quot;&gt;Referencing a figure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrosanct separation of text and figures means that in the main text, the commonly preferred way to refer to a figure is to put “Fig. X” in parentheses, e.g. (Fig. 2). You almost pretend that the figure doesn’t exist. When a figure is central to explaining something, that can lead to a rather silly repetition of references to the figure, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here is a sentence explaining something that can also be presented visually (Fig. 2). Of course, that sentence raises a second point about something adjacent, also included in the visuals (Fig. 2). When comparing those two ideas, we can derive some interesting results, such as this and that (Fig. 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There should be a way to integrate the text and figure without losing the advantages of separation. The proper path, it seems, is to make sure the figure stands on its own, but to reference it liberally in text. This suggests it’s okay to write e.g. “Figure 2 shows that …” or “Refer to figure 2 for a visual explanation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of multipart figures, the common practice of referring to a specific subfigure (e.g. Fig. 4B) is good, but it’s possible to do better. If part B of figure 4 happens to be in the top-right of the figure, you can specify that readers should look in the top-right: “as we can see in fig. 4B (top-right).” This is especially helpful if the “B” is small in the figure. That way, your readers will immediately know where to look. You don’t want them to waste their enegy trying to match the text and the visuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you control the final layout enough to know where the figures end up being printed relative to the text, it’s helpful to add indications like “on the next page” and such. (If you don’t control the final layout, then this is in the hands of editors, who should also follow my advice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, we also want to reference a figure that was shown much earlier. Ten pages into a paper, after you’ve been referencing Fig. 6 and Fig. 7, readers expect the next figure to be Fig. 8. If instead you refer to Fig. 1, it can be confusing because it doesn’t match the expectations, not to mention that Fig. 1 is probably on a distant page. You can alleviate that by explicitly saying you’re referring to something from earlier, e.g., “… as we saw in Fig. 1 from the introduction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, if you reference a color-coded part of the figure, there’s no rule against using color in the main text to ease the matching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abbreviations&quot;&gt;Abbreviations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/blog/2021/10/05/abbreviations.html&quot;&gt;post on abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;, I was pretty vehemently against them, or at least their proliferation. I would be more lenient in figures because spatial organization is more often a concern. If you have a plot with 30 lines and you want to label them all and they all refer to something like “Gross Domestic Product of the Democratic Republic of the Congo,” then yes, use abbreviations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s only if space and/or clutter are actually a concern! If the space you save thanks to an abbreviation remains blank, and if it doesn’t really declutter the figure, then you have made things harder for the reader, for no gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do use abbreviations, they have to be spelled in full somewhere close by. The standard way to do this is include them at the end of the caption, but this has the drawback of making the caption long and difficult to parse. A line of prose is also not the best way to format a list of abbreviations. If you can, a visual legend within the figure is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-stuff&quot;&gt;Other stuff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tables follow similar conventions than figures, and most of the advice here also applies to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the scope of JAWWS, another interesting improvement around figures would be to move towards a system where they can be published on their own, without being embedded in a paper, and have figure-makers be recognized for their work. But that’s a bigger change than just improving the norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid very dense figures and dense captions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When possible, use separate figures more than subfigures (unless it is relevant that the subfigures be together)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When using subfigures, make it clear where the captions for each subpart begin and end&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use color in captions and text when referencing a color-coded part of a picture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make use of your figures in the text; reference them in a way that makes things easier for reader&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abbreviations are okay to save visual space, but don’t overdo it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Click here for a summary of the main recommendations • This essay is part of the science style guide series Figures are the lifeblood of scientific papers. Many people won’t read your paper, but will look at the figures. Why is that? There are many reasons, ranging from being attracted to shiny colors to reducing cognitive load by activating a different part of memory. But I suspect that one of the most important reasons is that figures allow more freedom to writers than text. There are no word limits, fewer formatting constraints, no bad writing style norms. All that matters is that your figure is clear and true. Accordingly, scientists spend a lot of time on them, and they are often the best part of any scientific paper. Because of this freedom, I would say that figures are perhaps the part of scientific publishing that works best as thing currently stand. That doesn’t mean we can’t improve on them. Captions One of the norms I observe around figures is that they should be “separate” from the main text. The caption should be sufficient to understand a figure even if someone hasn’t read the text. This is a good idea overall, but it sometimes leads to paragraph-length captions that are as difficult to read as the main text. Not great. Journals also usually limit the number of figures you can have in a paper. This can lead to very dense figures, with multiple subparts (Fig. 1A, 1B, 1C, etc.), trying to cram as much information as possible. This is the visual equivalent to a long and dense paragraph. Also not great — plus it makes the captions even longer and confusing. Here’s an example figure and caption from the platypus paper I rewrote: Fig. 4. (A) Alignment of predicted protein sequence of transcripts containing a recombined VHδ gene isolated from platypus spleen RNA. The individual clones are identified by the last three digits of their GenBank accession numbers (JQ664690–JQ664710). Shown is the region from FR3 of the VHδ through the beginning of the Cδ domain. The sequence in bold at the top of the alignment is the germ-line VHδ and Cδ gene sequence. The double cysteines at the end of FR3 and unpaired cysteines in CDR3 are shaded, as is the canonical FGXG in FR4. (B) Nucleotide sequence of the CDR3 region of the eleven unique V(D)J recombinants using VHδ described in the text. The germ-line sequence of the 3′-end of VHδ, the two Dδ, are shown at the top. The germ-line Jδ sequences are shown on the right-hand side of the alignment interspersed amongst the cDNA sequences using each. Nucleotides in the junctions between the V, D, and J segments, shown italicized, are most likely N-nucleotides added by TdT. I’m sure all of it is essential information, so I won’t say that it should be shortened, exactly—although if you can, yes, shorten it! But it’s a figure. It’s supposed to be visual. As much of the caption as possible should be included directly in the figure. Then there’s the fact that Fig. 4 is in fact Fig. 4A and 4B. The “(B)” is buried in the middle of the caption, with no bolding or anything to make it stand out. Readers have to parse the caption themselves to understand the two parts separately. Plus, the text uses parentheses for normal parenthesis purposes, and even has a “(D)” that doesn’t refer to a hypothetical part D. This is asking a lot of effort from readers! I do like the fact that the caption refers to the main text (it says “described in the text” in part B), although it would have been nice if it said where to look exactly in the text. As things stand, the reader has to spend energy to find the spot being referred to. Also, if your caption contains the word “red” or “blue” or any color, and does not use the mentioned color, then you’re doing something wrong. Using color directly in a caption, to reference a color-coded part of the figure, helps your reader so much it would be mad not to do so. (There can be technical limitations, of course, but it’s not usually very difficult to add color to text. I wasn’t sure I could do it on this website, and it took three seconds of googling the relevant HTML snippet.) Referencing a figure The sacrosanct separation of text and figures means that in the main text, the commonly preferred way to refer to a figure is to put “Fig. X” in parentheses, e.g. (Fig. 2). You almost pretend that the figure doesn’t exist. When a figure is central to explaining something, that can lead to a rather silly repetition of references to the figure, like this: Here is a sentence explaining something that can also be presented visually (Fig. 2). Of course, that sentence raises a second point about something adjacent, also included in the visuals (Fig. 2). When comparing those two ideas, we can derive some interesting results, such as this and that (Fig. 2). There should be a way to integrate the text and figure without losing the advantages of separation. The proper path, it seems, is to make sure the figure stands on its own, but to reference it liberally in text. This suggests it’s okay to write e.g. “Figure 2 shows that …” or “Refer to figure 2 for a visual explanation.” In the case of multipart figures, the common practice of referring to a specific subfigure (e.g. Fig. 4B) is good, but it’s possible to do better. If part B of figure 4 happens to be in the top-right of the figure, you can specify that readers should look in the top-right: “as we can see in fig. 4B (top-right).” This is especially helpful if the “B” is small in the figure. That way, your readers will immediately know where to look. You don’t want them to waste their enegy trying to match the text and the visuals. Similarly, if you control the final layout enough to know where the figures end up being printed relative to the text, it’s helpful to add indications like “on the next page” and such. (If you don’t control the final layout, then this is in the hands of editors, who should also follow my advice.) Sometimes, we also want to reference a figure that was shown much earlier. Ten pages into a paper, after you’ve been referencing Fig. 6 and Fig. 7, readers expect the next figure to be Fig. 8. If instead you refer to Fig. 1, it can be confusing because it doesn’t match the expectations, not to mention that Fig. 1 is probably on a distant page. You can alleviate that by explicitly saying you’re referring to something from earlier, e.g., “… as we saw in Fig. 1 from the introduction.” And again, if you reference a color-coded part of the figure, there’s no rule against using color in the main text to ease the matching. Abbreviations In my post on abbreviations, I was pretty vehemently against them, or at least their proliferation. I would be more lenient in figures because spatial organization is more often a concern. If you have a plot with 30 lines and you want to label them all and they all refer to something like “Gross Domestic Product of the Democratic Republic of the Congo,” then yes, use abbreviations. But that’s only if space and/or clutter are actually a concern! If the space you save thanks to an abbreviation remains blank, and if it doesn’t really declutter the figure, then you have made things harder for the reader, for no gain. If you do use abbreviations, they have to be spelled in full somewhere close by. The standard way to do this is include them at the end of the caption, but this has the drawback of making the caption long and difficult to parse. A line of prose is also not the best way to format a list of abbreviations. If you can, a visual legend within the figure is better. Other stuff Tables follow similar conventions than figures, and most of the advice here also applies to them. Beyond the scope of JAWWS, another interesting improvement around figures would be to move towards a system where they can be published on their own, without being embedded in a paper, and have figure-makers be recognized for their work. But that’s a bigger change than just improving the norms. Recommendations Avoid very dense figures and dense captions When possible, use separate figures more than subfigures (unless it is relevant that the subfigures be together) When using subfigures, make it clear where the captions for each subpart begin and end Use color in captions and text when referencing a color-coded part of a picture Make use of your figures in the text; reference them in a way that makes things easier for reader Abbreviations are okay to save visual space, but don’t overdo it</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paper Review: Writing Accessible Theory in Ecology and Evolution: Insights from Cognitive Load Theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/01/15/writing-accessible-theory-ecology-evolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper Review: Writing Accessible Theory in Ecology and Evolution: Insights from Cognitive Load Theory" /><published>2022-01-15T15:05:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-15T15:05:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/01/15/writing-accessible-theory-ecology-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/01/15/writing-accessible-theory-ecology-evolution.html">&lt;p&gt;Serendipity struck this week as a fellow alumnus from my master’s degree in evolutionary biology, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/_Gil_Henriques&quot;&gt;Gil Henriques&lt;/a&gt;, co-authored a very relevant paper to my work on JAWWS: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/bioscience/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/biosci/biab133/6482999?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;Writing Accessible Theory in Ecology and Evolution: Insights from Cognitive Load Theory&lt;/a&gt; by Ou, Henriques et al. (unfortunately, it is behind a paywall).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ecology in evolution, as elsewhere, theory is heavy with math. But empiricists — the people who go into the field or the lab to collect data and perform experiments — tend to shy away from math. As a result, theoretical work is often ignored or incorrectly cited by the researchers who collect new data. One possible solution would be to improve the mathematical training of empirically-focussed biologists, but a big part of the responsibility rests on the people who try to communicate theory, i.e. the theoreticians themselves. How can they make their math more accessible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper focusses on the problem in ecology and evolutionay biology, but the recommendations easily generalize to any science in which there’s a dichotomy between theory and empiricism. Indeed, they generalize fairly well to almost any communication problems between scientists, which is exactly the point of JAWWS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cognitive-load-theory&quot;&gt;Cognitive load theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ou, Henriques et al. use the framing of cognitive load theory. Cognitive load is how much of short-term memory is being used when accomplishing a task such as reading and understanding a paper. This is very similar to something I’ve called “&lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/blog/2021/10/04/scientific-style-guide.html&quot;&gt;reading friction&lt;/a&gt;” in my essays: the principle of “making things easier for the reader.” Cognitive load theory formalizes this principle, which I’m thankful for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors explain that there are three types of cognitive load:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;intrinsic load&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the inherent complexity of a situation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;extraneous load&lt;/strong&gt; refers to complexity in the way the situation is presented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;germane load&lt;/strong&gt; refers to how much the situation is familiar to the reader. (More germane load = easier to link to known stuff, which is good. I find it confusing that one type of load is good and the other two are bad, but whatever.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t really do anything about intrinsic load: a problem is what it is, and unless you discuss an entirely different problem, there’s going to be some complexity to deal with. To make a paper more accessible, then, you can either increase germane load — i.e. make it easier for readers to link the theory with what they already know — or decrease extraneous load — i.e. make the presentation easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendations-to-increase-germane-load&quot;&gt;Recommendations to increase germane load&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ou, Henriques et al. recommend five strategies to help readers link complicated models with what they already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use metaphors and analogies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide narrative context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;State assumptions and explain their purpose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define terms and their biological meaning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide links to empirical research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these seem obvious but are worth insisting on — since things that seem obvious to a writer may not be obvious to a reader! For example, &lt;strong&gt;defining mathematical terms&lt;/strong&gt; (#4) isn’t groundbreaking advice, but it’s not uncommon for people to incorrectly assume that their readers know the terms. It could be due to not realizing that readers have a different background and therefore may interpret the terms in a way that you hadn’t thought of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendations #1 and #2 are rather basic techniques for making an argument, and yet &lt;strong&gt;metaphors, analogies, and narratives&lt;/strong&gt; are indeed used too rarely in scientific writing. A narrative means explaining your line of reasoning: what questions were you asking, why did you use some particular math technique, what did it tell you? For some reason, it’s often tempting to just give the final result of your thought process, but spelling it out is very often much clearer to readers. As for metaphors and analogies, everyone knows they are extremely useful, but, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/12/examples.html&quot;&gt;concrete examples&lt;/a&gt;, they can seem disposable when you’re limited by the word count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendation #3, about &lt;strong&gt;assumptions&lt;/strong&gt;, is also hugely important and not discussed enough in my experience. When you’re assuming something to simplify the world into a model, you have to say how and why! Otherwise it seems you’re not perfectly aware of what you’re doing, and your readers will be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendation #5 is interesting: in the context of biological theory, it says theoreticians should &lt;strong&gt;give suggestions of empirical experiments&lt;/strong&gt; that could validate the theory. When you present a model, you immediately ask, “How could we test this?” This can kickstart the readers’ thought process about the next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendations-to-decrease-extraneous-load&quot;&gt;Recommendations to decrease extraneous load&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors suggest four ways to remove the obstacles in the presentation of a theory paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adjust the level of mathematical detail and use signposting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use consistent and intuitive notation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide scripts and programs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualize models and results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjusting the level of math&lt;/strong&gt; (#1) is very much about &lt;em&gt;knowing your audience&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re writing for theoreticians, then a lot of equations can be fine; if you expect the paper to be read by empiricists, students, or a wider audience, then you should limit them. The same is true of jargon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendation #2 on &lt;strong&gt;consistent notation&lt;/strong&gt; is fairly obvious but again, it’s worth mentioning the obvious. Pick mathematical symbols that are easy to remember. Generalizing beyond math, you should also pick words and abbreviations that are easy to understand and consistent with established usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like #3 (&lt;strong&gt;sharing code and programs&lt;/strong&gt;) because it does not, like scientific publishing so often does, pretend that computers don’t exist. A lot of research these days use code, and it is a missed opportunity whenever that code isn’t accessible. Ou et al. also emphasize that comments in code are important, and suggest that some papers can benefit from a companion app (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mmosmond.shinyapps.io/criticalsplines/&quot;&gt;here’s an example app they give&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, recommendation #4 is about &lt;strong&gt;figures&lt;/strong&gt;. I think everyone agrees that providing visual support is generally a great idea, but their (visual!) illustration of this is so good that I’m reproducing their figure 2 here, with permission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/seed dispersion.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sections a, b, and c all illustrate the same model of seed dispersion on three islands. The first is three confusing equations. With some math knowledge you can gain an understanding of what they mean, but this takes time and effort. Section b is a highly abstract illustration of the same thing, where we can more intuitively grasp how seeds are dispersing between islands (or staying on the same island). But section c is where it suddenly becomes incredibly clear. Thanks to color, cartoons, and arrows, it takes seconds to understand what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper formalizes some of the stuff I’ve been discussing with using my own bespoke vocabulary, like “reading friction” instead of “cognitive load.” I suppose I was reinventing the wheel to some extent, not that there’s any shame in that. In fact, I’m happy to have found a more scholarly discussion of my ideas: it shows that some scientists also recognize that there are problems in intra-science communication and care about improving the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is specific to theoretical biology, but it generalizes well, and its specificity actually makes it pleasantly concrete. I imagine I will be referencing this paper a lot from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To critique the writing a little bit: it’s not a difficult paper to understand, but at times it feels a bit needlessly heavy, with long paragraphs and captions on the figures. Perhaps that’s a necessary thing to be taken seriously — as a science paper rather than a blog post — but it defeats the purpose a little bit. Also, ironically, the paper fails at least once at upholding its own recommendations. In figure 2 (the seed dispersion one above), the letter &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt; is used both as a parameter in the example model &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; as an identifier for the top-right subfigure. This goes against the idea that notation should be consistent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perfect is the enemy of good. Any improvement to intra-science communication is helpful, and this paper does a good job of recommending sensible techniques, especially when math is involved, as well as justifying them with cognitive load arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William J-A Ou, Gil J B Henriques, Athmanathan Senthilnathan, Po-Ju Ke, Tess N Grainger, Rachel M Germain, Writing Accessible Theory in Ecology and Evolution: Insights from Cognitive Load Theory, &lt;em&gt;BioScience&lt;/em&gt;, 2022; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/biosci/biab133&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/biosci/biab133&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Serendipity struck this week as a fellow alumnus from my master’s degree in evolutionary biology, Gil Henriques, co-authored a very relevant paper to my work on JAWWS: Writing Accessible Theory in Ecology and Evolution: Insights from Cognitive Load Theory by Ou, Henriques et al. (unfortunately, it is behind a paywall).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Platypus Paper, Rewritten</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/12/platypus-paper-rewritten.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Platypus Paper, Rewritten" /><published>2021-11-12T13:46:31-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-12T13:46:31-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/12/platypus-paper-rewritten</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/12/platypus-paper-rewritten.html">&lt;p&gt;This post contains a complete rewriting of the paper about platypuses and evolutionary immunology &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mbe/article/29/10/3205/1030857&quot;&gt;originally published&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;em&gt;Molecular Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/07/platypus-annotated.html&quot;&gt;also presented here with my annotations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to formatting constraints with footnotes, this post is not available on the JAWWS website, but it can be read in full &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/platypus-paper-rewritten/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This post contains a complete rewriting of the paper about platypuses and evolutionary immunology originally published at Molecular Ecology and Evolution, and also presented here with my annotations. Due to formatting constraints with footnotes, this post is not available on the JAWWS website, but it can be read in full here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Style Guide: Links</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/08/links-guidelines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Style Guide: Links" /><published>2021-11-08T13:46:31-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-08T13:46:31-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/08/links-guidelines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/08/links-guidelines.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was first published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/science-style-guide-links/&quot;&gt;Dark Gray Matters&lt;/a&gt; in November 2021. It is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/04/style-guide.html&quot;&gt;science style guide series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to Wikipedia and start reading an article on some topic you don’t know much about. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umami&quot;&gt;umami taste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances are that by the end of the first few paragraph, you will have clicked on several links, either because they referred to terms you didn’t know (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glutamic_acid&quot;&gt;glutamate&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inosine_monophosphate&quot; title=&quot;Inosine monophosphate&quot;&gt;inosine monophosphate&lt;/a&gt;), or because you were curious (what does Wikipedia have to say about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taste#Basic_tastes&quot;&gt;five basic tastes&lt;/a&gt;?). Now these links might be open in new tabs for you to check later. Or maybe you’ve already given up reading the original umami article, and are now exploring some new rabbit hole (e.g. the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scoville_scale&quot;&gt;Scoville scale of spiciness&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia is a great resource for many reasons, but one of them is this constant hyperlinking to other relevant Wikipedia articles. This has a major advantage: &lt;strong&gt;it allows the reader to create their own reading experience&lt;/strong&gt;. Advanced readers on some topic can keep reading without having to go through the basics they already know. Beginner readers can look up technical terms easily. Wikipedia is a choose-your-own-adventure book, where you can wander according to your own character level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links are even an answer to some degree to the four-way tradeoff I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.substack.com/p/the-four-way-tradeoff-of-the-writer&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It’s difficult to write something that is clear, brief, complex, and information-rich. But Wikipedia articles come closer to the golden middle, and that’s thanks to links. With no need to explain every difficult term directly in the text, articles can be more brief without sacrificing clarity. By packaging complex information in other articles, and showing only the link, Wikipedia articles can contain more complexity and richness of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The reason it doesn’t falsify my four-way tradeoff theory is that Wikipedia &lt;em&gt;as a whole&lt;/em&gt; cannot be called succinct. To understand a topic well, you still have to read a lot of articles. But Wikipedia packages this information in relatively brief articles. In other words, information architecture is a pretty good solution to the tradeoff.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links make matters easier to readers, but they also help writers. You don’t have to do as much guessing about what your audience knows; your audience will decide for themselves. And you can just reuse existing information written by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggests that our &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/proposal-for-a-new-scientific-writing-guide/&quot;&gt;two principles&lt;/a&gt; are satisfied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimum reading friction&lt;/strong&gt;: links give agency to readers. They make it easier to look up complex terms (which readers will tend to google anyway).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-hanging fruit&lt;/strong&gt;: adding links to existing public resources like Wikipedia, other encyclopedias, or open-access papers, is an easy thing to do for a writer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links-in-scientific-papers&quot;&gt;Links in scientific papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all of the above, we’d expect scientific papers — which are almost always at the frontier of the tradeoff, trying to cram a lot of complex information within a word limit without being too difficult to read — to use hyperlinks heavily. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. They rarely do. At most they include citations that link to the reference section, which &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; include a link to the original paper, which may or may not be openly accessible to you, and which may or may not be a 10-page difficult read in which the explanation you seek is buried in page three of the discussion with no hint to tell you where to look. And they definitely never include links to Wikipedia or anything like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is that? I’m guessing part of the explanation is the high importance of those citations. It is considered vital to put your work in relation to existing literature, so scientists have an incentive to reference as many relevant papers as they can, and no incentive to link to anything else. The respectability of the sources comes into play; Wikipedia isn’t a reputable source (it can be edited by anyone! It’s not peer-reviewed!!), nor are a lot of the other websites you could link to. So they tend to be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the requirements of proper information management. References must be written in standard format. So if for some reason you do need to link to a website, then you’ll have to use a format like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/Food/IngredientsPackagingLabeling/FoodAdditivesIngredients/ucm328728.htm&quot;&gt;“Questions and Answers on Monosodium glutamate (MSG)”&lt;/a&gt;. Silver Spring, Maryland: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Food_and_Drug_Administration&quot; title=&quot;United States Food and Drug Administration&quot;&gt;United States Food and Drug Administration&lt;/a&gt;. 19 November 2012. Retrieved 19 February 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are good reasons to this formalism. But it also means that adding any link to a paper requires some work. As a result, I suspect it leads to less hyperlinking in science papers than would be useful to readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever read a scientific paper, it’s likely that you have googled complicated terms and looked up Wikipedia articles to help you. Scientists shouldn’t pretend that this isn’t happening. They should not hesitate to add link to resources like Wikipedia, blogs, Twitter threads, and other papers, in order to guide readers and reduce friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drawbacks&quot;&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few drawbacks to hyperlinked text. None of them invalidate the idea that links should be used more, but we should keep them in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One drawback is that links can be &lt;strong&gt;distracting&lt;/strong&gt;. A barrage of links in a paragraph might be somewhat annoying to read. (Although links also have the benefit of providing novelty to text — even a simple thing like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/02/20/writing-advice/&quot;&gt;color of a hyperlink&lt;/a&gt; can be useful to make a piece of writing less boring.) And having to open links may drive readers away from the original paper, and require some more effort on their part as opposed to a piece written in a way that beginners don’t need to look up extra information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major drawback is &lt;strong&gt;link rot&lt;/strong&gt;. A webpage may stop existing at any moment, and then your link becomes useless. Also, Wikipedia articles can change and stop fulfilling their original purpose. (Although in practice Wikipedia contributors are mindful of that and use redirections a lot.) One way to circumvent this is to link to archived pages, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/&quot;&gt;Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, links don’t work &lt;strong&gt;offline&lt;/strong&gt;. But my contention is that fewer and fewer people are reading papers in print or without internet access. We shouldn’t make it impossible for these modes of reading to happen, but it’s time we make full use of the web’s possibilities to improve science publishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not hesitate to add links to various resources, including encyclopedias, your own content (whether formally published or not), etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to find the correct balance between too few and too many links.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your paper should be readable without clicking any links, so do explain the crucial parts directly in the text.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Too many links can be distracting, so choose carefully when to add one.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Link to archived webpages when possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Links shouldn’t replace formal citations, but it’s good practice to pair citations with direct links to make it easier to look up the reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This essay was first published on Dark Gray Matters in November 2021. It is part of the science style guide series. Go to Wikipedia and start reading an article on some topic you don’t know much about. For example, the umami taste. Chances are that by the end of the first few paragraph, you will have clicked on several links, either because they referred to terms you didn’t know (glutamate, inosine monophosphate), or because you were curious (what does Wikipedia have to say about the five basic tastes?). Now these links might be open in new tabs for you to check later. Or maybe you’ve already given up reading the original umami article, and are now exploring some new rabbit hole (e.g. the Scoville scale of spiciness). Wikipedia is a great resource for many reasons, but one of them is this constant hyperlinking to other relevant Wikipedia articles. This has a major advantage: it allows the reader to create their own reading experience. Advanced readers on some topic can keep reading without having to go through the basics they already know. Beginner readers can look up technical terms easily. Wikipedia is a choose-your-own-adventure book, where you can wander according to your own character level. Links are even an answer to some degree to the four-way tradeoff I wrote about here. It’s difficult to write something that is clear, brief, complex, and information-rich. But Wikipedia articles come closer to the golden middle, and that’s thanks to links. With no need to explain every difficult term directly in the text, articles can be more brief without sacrificing clarity. By packaging complex information in other articles, and showing only the link, Wikipedia articles can contain more complexity and richness of information. (The reason it doesn’t falsify my four-way tradeoff theory is that Wikipedia as a whole cannot be called succinct. To understand a topic well, you still have to read a lot of articles. But Wikipedia packages this information in relatively brief articles. In other words, information architecture is a pretty good solution to the tradeoff.) Links make matters easier to readers, but they also help writers. You don’t have to do as much guessing about what your audience knows; your audience will decide for themselves. And you can just reuse existing information written by others. This suggests that our two principles are satisfied: Minimum reading friction: links give agency to readers. They make it easier to look up complex terms (which readers will tend to google anyway). Low-hanging fruit: adding links to existing public resources like Wikipedia, other encyclopedias, or open-access papers, is an easy thing to do for a writer. Links in scientific papers Given all of the above, we’d expect scientific papers — which are almost always at the frontier of the tradeoff, trying to cram a lot of complex information within a word limit without being too difficult to read — to use hyperlinks heavily. Right? Nope. They rarely do. At most they include citations that link to the reference section, which may include a link to the original paper, which may or may not be openly accessible to you, and which may or may not be a 10-page difficult read in which the explanation you seek is buried in page three of the discussion with no hint to tell you where to look. And they definitely never include links to Wikipedia or anything like it. Why is that? I’m guessing part of the explanation is the high importance of those citations. It is considered vital to put your work in relation to existing literature, so scientists have an incentive to reference as many relevant papers as they can, and no incentive to link to anything else. The respectability of the sources comes into play; Wikipedia isn’t a reputable source (it can be edited by anyone! It’s not peer-reviewed!!), nor are a lot of the other websites you could link to. So they tend to be avoided. Then there’s the requirements of proper information management. References must be written in standard format. So if for some reason you do need to link to a website, then you’ll have to use a format like: “Questions and Answers on Monosodium glutamate (MSG)”. Silver Spring, Maryland: United States Food and Drug Administration. 19 November 2012. Retrieved 19 February 2017. There are good reasons to this formalism. But it also means that adding any link to a paper requires some work. As a result, I suspect it leads to less hyperlinking in science papers than would be useful to readers. If you’ve ever read a scientific paper, it’s likely that you have googled complicated terms and looked up Wikipedia articles to help you. Scientists shouldn’t pretend that this isn’t happening. They should not hesitate to add link to resources like Wikipedia, blogs, Twitter threads, and other papers, in order to guide readers and reduce friction. Drawbacks There are a few drawbacks to hyperlinked text. None of them invalidate the idea that links should be used more, but we should keep them in mind. One drawback is that links can be distracting. A barrage of links in a paragraph might be somewhat annoying to read. (Although links also have the benefit of providing novelty to text — even a simple thing like the color of a hyperlink can be useful to make a piece of writing less boring.) And having to open links may drive readers away from the original paper, and require some more effort on their part as opposed to a piece written in a way that beginners don’t need to look up extra information. Another major drawback is link rot. A webpage may stop existing at any moment, and then your link becomes useless. Also, Wikipedia articles can change and stop fulfilling their original purpose. (Although in practice Wikipedia contributors are mindful of that and use redirections a lot.) One way to circumvent this is to link to archived pages, such as the Wayback Machine. And of course, links don’t work offline. But my contention is that fewer and fewer people are reading papers in print or without internet access. We shouldn’t make it impossible for these modes of reading to happen, but it’s time we make full use of the web’s possibilities to improve science publishing. Recommendations Do not hesitate to add links to various resources, including encyclopedias, your own content (whether formally published or not), etc. Try to find the correct balance between too few and too many links. Your paper should be readable without clicking any links, so do explain the crucial parts directly in the text. Too many links can be distracting, so choose carefully when to add one. Link to archived webpages when possible. Links shouldn’t replace formal citations, but it’s good practice to pair citations with direct links to make it easier to look up the reference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Style Guide: Bullet Points</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/26/bullet-points.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Style Guide: Bullet Points" /><published>2021-10-26T14:46:31-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-26T14:46:31-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/26/bullet-points</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/26/bullet-points.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was first published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/science-style-guide-bullet-points/&quot;&gt;Dark Gray Matters&lt;/a&gt; in October 2021. It is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/04/style-guide.html&quot;&gt;science style guide series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing with bullet points (or bullet numbers, letters etc.) has several advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It provides clear guidance to readers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It forces the writer to think about the structure of what they’re trying to say.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It comes with built-in line breaks, which tends to create shorter, more readable paragraphs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It breaks the flow of normal prose, which makes reading less monotonous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is another channel to communicate emphasis (in addition to italics, bold, caps, subheadings, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything in a piece of writing should follow point form format. Regular prose, organized in paragraphs, is better for most things. But when you are trying to express something that’s highly structured, like a list of steps (in a recipe, or in an experimental protocol), then &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; using bulleted lists can work against you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science papers being a weirdly conservative genre, bulleted lists are somewhat uncommon in them. Papers will quite often use quasi-point form formats, like (1) having numbers or letters in the middle of a paragraph, like this; (2) using “first,” “second,” “third”; or (3) separating ideas with quasi-titles written in italics or bold, but without a line break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see this a lot in figures. Many scientific figures are complex and contain multiple parts. Each part is identified with a letter, as in the following example from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/an-annotated-reading-of-a-paper-about-platypuses/&quot;&gt;platypus paper&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2021/10/mss128f5-630x1024.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the caption will have long explanations separated by very easy to miss letters, like this. (A) The first part of the figure, including some colors and shapes. (B) The second part. Note that this part comes after the first part, and before part C. (C) The third part. I’m running out pointless things to write, but I want this to be a wall of text, so I’m gonna keep writing. (D) Have you lost attention yet? (E) That’s a lot of parts, isn’t it? Funny thing, there’s a limitation of how I do image captions that wouldn’t even let me use bullet points even if I wanted to. (F) At last, the final part. So much information needed to make sense of this picture, right? It’s good to be exhaustive, but there’s no point in making it difficult for readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of these habits come, I assume, from the fact that journals used to be available only in print. Space was very limited, and there’s often a lot of scientific information to display, so you’re not going to waste any with bullet points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we don’t have these limitations. Using bullet points where appropriate is nice to your readers, so use them. They’re an easy way to &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/science-style-guide-giving-examples/#:~:text=Minimum%20Reading%20Friction%20principle&quot;&gt;reduce reading friction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re also clearly a &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/proposal-for-a-new-scientific-writing-guide/#low-hanging-fruit&quot;&gt;Low-Hanging Fruit&lt;/a&gt;. Similar to breaking paragraphs, it takes very little work to turn a piece of text into a list, if it’s already presenting the information in something close to a list. (If it isn’t, then bullet points probably won’t work well anyway.) It’s also one of those interventions that can be done almost mechanistically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use bullet points liberally when it is appropriate, e.g. for:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Steps in a process, experiment, protocol, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lists of materials used, substances, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enumerations (e.g. “the five characteristics of X are : …”)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nested bullet points (just like the above) can be useful, but don’t overuse them.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At more than two levels, the information structure is probably too complex for the bullet points to improve readability.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick bullet points instead of numbers/letters when the order does not matter. Pick numbers (for simplicity, prefer Arabic numerals, but Roman numerals can work) or letters when the order does matter (e.g. for steps in a protocol).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bullet points are useful to break the monotony of reading paragraphs, but when there’s too much point form, the reverse becomes true. Use bulleted lists less than normal prose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This essay was first published on Dark Gray Matters in October 2021. It is part of the science style guide series. Writing with bullet points (or bullet numbers, letters etc.) has several advantages: It provides clear guidance to readers. It forces the writer to think about the structure of what they’re trying to say. It comes with built-in line breaks, which tends to create shorter, more readable paragraphs. It breaks the flow of normal prose, which makes reading less monotonous. It is another channel to communicate emphasis (in addition to italics, bold, caps, subheadings, etc.). Not everything in a piece of writing should follow point form format. Regular prose, organized in paragraphs, is better for most things. But when you are trying to express something that’s highly structured, like a list of steps (in a recipe, or in an experimental protocol), then not using bulleted lists can work against you. Science papers being a weirdly conservative genre, bulleted lists are somewhat uncommon in them. Papers will quite often use quasi-point form formats, like (1) having numbers or letters in the middle of a paragraph, like this; (2) using “first,” “second,” “third”; or (3) separating ideas with quasi-titles written in italics or bold, but without a line break. You see this a lot in figures. Many scientific figures are complex and contain multiple parts. Each part is identified with a letter, as in the following example from the platypus paper: And the caption will have long explanations separated by very easy to miss letters, like this. (A) The first part of the figure, including some colors and shapes. (B) The second part. Note that this part comes after the first part, and before part C. (C) The third part. I’m running out pointless things to write, but I want this to be a wall of text, so I’m gonna keep writing. (D) Have you lost attention yet? (E) That’s a lot of parts, isn’t it? Funny thing, there’s a limitation of how I do image captions that wouldn’t even let me use bullet points even if I wanted to. (F) At last, the final part. So much information needed to make sense of this picture, right? It’s good to be exhaustive, but there’s no point in making it difficult for readers. A lot of these habits come, I assume, from the fact that journals used to be available only in print. Space was very limited, and there’s often a lot of scientific information to display, so you’re not going to waste any with bullet points. Today we don’t have these limitations. Using bullet points where appropriate is nice to your readers, so use them. They’re an easy way to reduce reading friction. They’re also clearly a Low-Hanging Fruit. Similar to breaking paragraphs, it takes very little work to turn a piece of text into a list, if it’s already presenting the information in something close to a list. (If it isn’t, then bullet points probably won’t work well anyway.) It’s also one of those interventions that can be done almost mechanistically. Recommendations Use bullet points liberally when it is appropriate, e.g. for: Steps in a process, experiment, protocol, etc. Lists of materials used, substances, etc. Enumerations (e.g. “the five characteristics of X are : …”) Nested bullet points (just like the above) can be useful, but don’t overuse them. At more than two levels, the information structure is probably too complex for the bullet points to improve readability. Pick bullet points instead of numbers/letters when the order does not matter. Pick numbers (for simplicity, prefer Arabic numerals, but Roman numerals can work) or letters when the order does matter (e.g. for steps in a protocol). Bullet points are useful to break the monotony of reading paragraphs, but when there’s too much point form, the reverse becomes true. Use bulleted lists less than normal prose.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science Style Guide: Giving Examples</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/12/examples.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science Style Guide: Giving Examples" /><published>2021-10-12T14:46:31-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T14:46:31-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/12/examples</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/12/examples.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was first published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/science-style-guide-giving-examples/&quot;&gt;Dark Gray Matters&lt;/a&gt; in October 2021. It is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jawws.org/blog/2021/10/04/style-guide.html&quot;&gt;science style guide series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you’re writing a science paper. The journal you’re going to submit it to specifies a word limit: 5,000 max. You open the stats in your finished draft — 5,523 words. You’re going to have to cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem is: everything you wrote is important! You can’t take out anything from the Methods or Results sections: that would make the study weaker and less likely to be accepted for publication. You can’t take out any of the background information in the introduction: you already included the bare minimum for readers to understand the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, on closer inspection, perhaps not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; the bare minimum. You reread this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most models of trait evolution are based on Brownian motion, which assumes that a trait (say, beak size in some group of bird species) changes randomly, with some species evolving a larger beak, some a smaller one, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you removed the parts that talk about beak size? That’s not &lt;em&gt;strictly&lt;/em&gt; necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most models of trait evolution are based on Brownian motion, which assumes that a trait changes randomly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we go. More concise, more to the point, and most importantly, you shaved off 23 words from that word count. Of course, the sentence is less illustrative, but whatever: your readers are smart, they’ll be able to figure out an example on their own. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, okay, not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; wrong, your readers probably &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; smart. But this goes against the &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/proposal-for-a-new-scientific-writing-guide/#minimum-reading-friction&quot;&gt;Minimum Reading Friction&lt;/a&gt; principle. The point of most writing, including science papers, is to do the work so that readers don’t need to. If readers need to think of an illustrative example themselves to fully understand your abstract idea, then you’re asking a big effort of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picking good, concrete, relevant examples is a lot of work, whether as a reader or writer.1 I realize this constantly when I write. It’s very tempting to just state an abstract idea and not bother finding a good example to illustrate it. After all, the abstract idea is more general and therefore more valuable — provided that your readers understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggled with example-finding in this very essay. It took me a while to think of the opening about cutting examples to respect a word count limit. And I’m not even that happy with this example. For one thing, it’s not very concrete. For another, it’s not even the most common reason for lack of examples: usually, we don’t cut them out, we simply fail to come up with them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, unfortunately, this piece of guidance is less of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/proposal-for-a-new-scientific-writing-guide/#low-hanging-fruit&quot;&gt;Low-Hanging Fruit&lt;/a&gt; than others: adding good examples is a skill that takes some practice. At the very least, it’s not difficult from the point of view of structure, since it doesn’t require you to rethink your argument — you usually just need to add a sentence or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few other minor points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;where-should-examples-be-placed-relative-to-the-main-idea&quot;&gt;Where should examples be placed relative to the main idea?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s most intuitive to place an example right after the idea it supports, and that’s probably fine most of the time. But there are benefits to placing an example first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Left-handedness seems to be somewhat correlated with extraordinary success, including political success. For example, despite a base rate of about 10% left-handedness in the general population, four of the seven last United States presidents — Barack Obama, Bill Clinton, George H.W. Bush, and Ronald Reagan — were left-handed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;vs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What do US presidents Barack Obama, Bill Clinton, George H.W. Bush, and Ronald Reagan have in common? They were all left-handed. In other words, four of the last seven presidents were left-handed, compared to a base rate in the general population of about 10%. This suggests that left-handedness is correlated with extraordinary success, at least in politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the second version more engaging. You see an interesting fact, you’re drawn in, and then the writer tells you the more general point when you’re most receptive to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalists do this a lot. They open with a story, and then proceed to make their point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-types-of-scientific-writing-does-this-apply-to&quot;&gt;What types of scientific writing does this apply to?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything that deals mostly with abstract ideas. Highly concrete writing, such as the sections describing the methods or results of a study, aren’t concerned. Thus, in a typical experiment paper, this advice is mostly relevant to the discussion section and some of the introductory background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors of literature reviews may need to be more careful. These papers integrate a lot of ideas from reviewed studies; it can be tempting to skip examples in order to include more content in less space. The paragraph I worked on &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.com/dgm/appendix-to-jawws-an-incrementally-rewritten-paragraph/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; was from a literature review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-word-limits-though&quot;&gt;What about word limits, though?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you really are constrained by externally imposed word limits, and sometimes the examples really are the the least problematic thing to take out. In those cases, well, do what you have to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JAWWS, I don’t want to be strict about word limits. They often force writers to sacrifice clarity to satisfy other components of &lt;a href=&quot;https://etiennefd.substack.com/p/the-four-way-tradeoff-of-the-writer&quot;&gt;the four-way tradeoff&lt;/a&gt;. They’re also not as relevant in an age where papers are rarely printed on, well, paper. On the other hand, I imagine that many other publications first think that and then have to implement limits to avoid very long submissions. I wonder if the solution could be to make concrete examples not count, provided it’s not too difficult to identify them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support each abstract idea with at least one example
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Complicated abstract idea may benefit from multiple examples&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose concrete, specific examples that can be grasped immediately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When possible, put the example before stating the underlying idea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also&quot;&gt;See also&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slate Star Codex’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/02/20/writing-advice&quot;&gt;Nonfiction Writing Advice&lt;/a&gt;, section 6 “Use concrete examples”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This essay was first published on Dark Gray Matters in October 2021. It is part of the science style guide series. Imagine you’re writing a science paper. The journal you’re going to submit it to specifies a word limit: 5,000 max. You open the stats in your finished draft — 5,523 words. You’re going to have to cut. Problem is: everything you wrote is important! You can’t take out anything from the Methods or Results sections: that would make the study weaker and less likely to be accepted for publication. You can’t take out any of the background information in the introduction: you already included the bare minimum for readers to understand the rest. Although, on closer inspection, perhaps not quite the bare minimum. You reread this sentence: Most models of trait evolution are based on Brownian motion, which assumes that a trait (say, beak size in some group of bird species) changes randomly, with some species evolving a larger beak, some a smaller one, etc. What if you removed the parts that talk about beak size? That’s not strictly necessary. Most models of trait evolution are based on Brownian motion, which assumes that a trait changes randomly. There we go. More concise, more to the point, and most importantly, you shaved off 23 words from that word count. Of course, the sentence is less illustrative, but whatever: your readers are smart, they’ll be able to figure out an example on their own. Right? Wrong. Well, okay, not quite wrong, your readers probably are smart. But this goes against the Minimum Reading Friction principle. The point of most writing, including science papers, is to do the work so that readers don’t need to. If readers need to think of an illustrative example themselves to fully understand your abstract idea, then you’re asking a big effort of them. Picking good, concrete, relevant examples is a lot of work, whether as a reader or writer.1 I realize this constantly when I write. It’s very tempting to just state an abstract idea and not bother finding a good example to illustrate it. After all, the abstract idea is more general and therefore more valuable — provided that your readers understand it. I struggled with example-finding in this very essay. It took me a while to think of the opening about cutting examples to respect a word count limit. And I’m not even that happy with this example. For one thing, it’s not very concrete. For another, it’s not even the most common reason for lack of examples: usually, we don’t cut them out, we simply fail to come up with them in the first place. And so, unfortunately, this piece of guidance is less of a Low-Hanging Fruit than others: adding good examples is a skill that takes some practice. At the very least, it’s not difficult from the point of view of structure, since it doesn’t require you to rethink your argument — you usually just need to add a sentence or two. Here are a few other minor points: Where should examples be placed relative to the main idea? It’s most intuitive to place an example right after the idea it supports, and that’s probably fine most of the time. But there are benefits to placing an example first. Consider: Left-handedness seems to be somewhat correlated with extraordinary success, including political success. For example, despite a base rate of about 10% left-handedness in the general population, four of the seven last United States presidents — Barack Obama, Bill Clinton, George H.W. Bush, and Ronald Reagan — were left-handed. vs. What do US presidents Barack Obama, Bill Clinton, George H.W. Bush, and Ronald Reagan have in common? They were all left-handed. In other words, four of the last seven presidents were left-handed, compared to a base rate in the general population of about 10%. This suggests that left-handedness is correlated with extraordinary success, at least in politics. I find the second version more engaging. You see an interesting fact, you’re drawn in, and then the writer tells you the more general point when you’re most receptive to it. Journalists do this a lot. They open with a story, and then proceed to make their point. What types of scientific writing does this apply to? Anything that deals mostly with abstract ideas. Highly concrete writing, such as the sections describing the methods or results of a study, aren’t concerned. Thus, in a typical experiment paper, this advice is mostly relevant to the discussion section and some of the introductory background. Authors of literature reviews may need to be more careful. These papers integrate a lot of ideas from reviewed studies; it can be tempting to skip examples in order to include more content in less space. The paragraph I worked on here was from a literature review. What about word limits, though? Sometimes you really are constrained by externally imposed word limits, and sometimes the examples really are the the least problematic thing to take out. In those cases, well, do what you have to do. In JAWWS, I don’t want to be strict about word limits. They often force writers to sacrifice clarity to satisfy other components of the four-way tradeoff. They’re also not as relevant in an age where papers are rarely printed on, well, paper. On the other hand, I imagine that many other publications first think that and then have to implement limits to avoid very long submissions. I wonder if the solution could be to make concrete examples not count, provided it’s not too difficult to identify them. Recommendations Support each abstract idea with at least one example Complicated abstract idea may benefit from multiple examples Choose concrete, specific examples that can be grasped immediately When possible, put the example before stating the underlying idea See also Slate Star Codex’s Nonfiction Writing Advice, section 6 “Use concrete examples”</summary></entry></feed>